Guide to the Witold Gombrowicz Archive
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Witold Gombrowicz archive
1902-1998
GEN MSS 515
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
144.46
(148 boxes) + 97 broadside folders, cold storage
The archive consists of correspondence, writings, personal papers, photographs, audiovisual material and memorabilia documenting Gombrowicz's life and literary activity chiefly during the last two decades of his life (1949-69). Series I, Correspondence, contains personal and professional correspondence. There is correspondence with family, Polish and European literary and cultural figures, other Polish emigres, and Latin American friends and writers. There is considerable correspondence with editors and publishers, including Jerzy Giedroyc, the Polish editor of Gombrowicz's works. Other Polish correspondents include Tadeusz Breza, Zofia Chadzynska, Jozef Czapski, Maria Dabrowska, Jaroslaw Iwaszkiewicz, Constantin Jelenski, Tadeusz Kantor, Maria Szczepanska Kuncewiczowa, Czeslaw Milosz, Zygmunt Mycielski, Artur Sandauer, Leopold Tyrmand, Kaimierz Wierzynski, and Jozef Wittlin. Series II, Writings of Gombrowicz, consists of novels, plays, shorter works, autobiographical writings, and other writings. There are drafts and printed versions of shorter works, including stories, articles, interviews, and open letters. There are drafts of more significant works, including: holograph and typescript drafts of the novel Kosmos; holograph and typescript drafts of the play Operetka; drafts, with many fragments, of different Dziennik (diaries); and a typescript draft of Guide de la philosophie en six heures un quart. Series III, Adaptations by Others of Gombrowicz's Works, contains theater scenarios, film treatments, and other material based on works by Gombrowicz. Series IV, Theater Programs, contains programs for theatrical adaptations of Gombrowicz's works. Series V, Writings of Others About Gombrowicz, contains articles, bibliographies, published letters, transcripts for radio broadcasts, theses and student papers, and material related to a special issue of the journal L'Herne, devoted to Gombrowicz, edited by Constantin Jelenski and Dominique de Roux. Series VI, Commemorative Works and Activities, consists of obituaries and tributes issued in the months following Gombrowicz's death, and correspondence, organizational records, and printed material from commemorative events dating from the late 1980s. Series VII, Audiovisual Materials, includes both audio recordings and moving image media. Audio recordings encompass recordings of programs about Gombrowicz and adaptations of his works for radio. Moving image media includes amateur films, documentaries about Gombrowicz, and theater and film productions of Gombrowicz's works. Series VIII and IX consist of Photographs and Personal Papers respectively. There are photograph albums of Gombrowicz for periods in Poland, Argentina, and Europe, and later photographs of theater and film productions and commemorative events. Personal Papers includes personal documents, family papers relating to the history of the Gombrowicz family, and a small number of writings by family members. Series X, Rita Gombrowicz Papers, contains material gathered by Gombrowicz's wife following his death, and is organized into subseries for correspondence, research files, writings, clippings, and printed ephemera. Series XI, Clippings, consists of printed material, including journals, book catalogues, printed ephemera, and clippings of articles related directly to Gombrowicz and his work. Series XII, Posters, includes posters for plays, exhibitions, films, and festivals by Polish poster artists Franciszek Starowieyski, Jan Lenica, Waldemar Swierzy, Wiktor Sadowski, Wieslaw Walkuski, and others.
Gombrowicz, Witold, 1904-1969
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired from Rita Gombrowicz by purchase through Sotheby's France in 1998 and by gift in 2006.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 115-136 and items in cold storage: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
WITOLD GOMBROWICZ (1904-1969)
Witold Gombrowicz was one of the most influential Polish writers of the 20th century, author of novels, plays, short stories, essays, and a diary.
The following chronology lists the dates of key events in his life and the dates of first publication of works in Polish:
1904 Aug 4: born in Maloszyce near Opatów (Poland) to a family of landowning nobility, fourth child of Jan Onufry Gombrowicz and Antonina Gombrowicz (p.v. Kotkowska)
1911: moves to Warsaw
1915-22: attends Osmioklasowe Gimnazjum Meskie Kola Szkolnego im. sw. Stanislawa Kostki
1922-27: studies law at Warsaw University
1928: works as a judicial assistant
1933: Pamietnik z okresu dojrzewania published
1937: Ferdydurke published
1938: Iwona, ksiezniczka Burgunda published
1939: Opetani published in the press
1939 Aug 31: travels to Argentina and remains there in 24-year exile
1947: translation of Ferdydurke into Spanish
1947-55: works at Banco Polaco in Buenos Aires
1951: starts collaboration with Polish monthly Kultura; Transatlantyk (fragments) published
1953: Slub and Trans-Atlantyk published
1957: Dziennik 1953-57 published
1959-61: writes series of radio talks published posthumously as Wspomnienia polskie/Wedrówki po Argentynie
1960: Pornografia published
1962: Dziennik 1957-61 published
1963 Apr 8: leaves Argentina
1963 May - 1964 May: stays in Berlin as a guest of the Ford Foundation
1964 May - Sep: stays in Royaumont, France
1964 Oct: relocates to Vence, France
1965: Kosmos published
1966: Dziennik 1961-66 and Operetka published
1967: receives Le Prix International des Éditeurs (Formentor)
1968: marries Marie-Rita Labrosse
1969: Entretiens avec Dominique de Roux published (in French); gives a series of lessons on philosophy to his wife Rita and Dominique de Roux, published posthumously under the title Guide de la philosophie en six heures un quart
1969 Jul 24: dies in Vence
Scope and Contents
The Witold Gombrowicz Archive documents Gombrowicz's life and literary output chiefly during the last two decades of his life (1949-69), as well as the reception of his works after his death. Due to his unexpected exile from Poland following the onset of World War II, and the difficulties he faced during his first few years in Argentina, the collection contains relatively little material from the time of his birth in 1904 through 1949.
The archive consists of Witold Gombrowicz's personal papers, material that was in his possession at the time of his death, and material later added by his wife Rita Gombrowicz. Gombrowicz's personal papers include correspondence, manuscripts of his writings, writings of others, newspaper clippings (some of which Gombrowicz annotated), photo albums, and personal papers. Rita Gombrowicz supplemented these materials with copies of Gombrowicz's outgoing correspondence, other documentation of his life, including his family background, and some literary manuscripts and related material. Other materials principally contributed by Rita Gombrowicz include theater programs relating to productions of Gombrowicz's works and to the Polish theater more generally, posters, audio recordings and video tapes, typescripts of adaptations of Gombrowicz's works by others, photographs documenting productions of his works, writings by others about Gombrowicz, additional clippings files, commemorative material, and Gombrowicz-related printed ephemera. The archive also includes Rita Gombrowicz's papers relating to her research on her husband and to her management of his literary affairs following his death.
Much of the archive is in Polish. To aid researchers, the spelling of Polish words and proper names has been simplified and diacritic symbols have been omitted. In the latter case, the Polish characters "l with stroke" or "a with ogonek" are treated respectively as "l" and "a" in the alphabetical listing. A noteworthy feature of the archive is, however, the extraordinary range of languages represented in the material, reflecting the breadth of Gombrowicz's influence. In addition to Polish, the languages most heavily represented are French, Spanish, German, and English. The archive includes material written in Bosnian, Bulgarian, Czech, Danish, Dutch, Finnish, Greek, Hebrew, Hungarian, Italian, Japanese, Lithuanian, Portuguese, Rumanian, Russian, Serbian, Slovak, Swedish, Turkish, and Yiddish.
The archive is housed in 137 boxes and organized into twelve series: Correspondence, Writings of Gombrowicz, Adaptations by Others of Gombrowicz's Works, Theatre Programs, Writings by Others About Gombrowicz, Commemorative Works and Activities, Audiovisual Materials, Photographs, Personal Papers, Rita Gombrowicz Papers, Clippings, and Posters.
Series I, Correspondence, encompasses personal (including family) and literary and business correspondence, as well as fan mail, arranged in a single alphabetical run by name of correspondent. Incoming and outgoing correspondence is interfiled.
A significant portion of the correspondence includes originals of incoming letters and carbons of outgoing letters. The correspondence also includes photocopies and transcripts, added by Rita Gombrowicz, of original letters held in private hands or in public institutions (chiefly the Muzeum Literatury im. Adama Mickiewicza w Warszawie). Rita Gombrowicz's processing notes, which contextualize the contents of folders, have also been retained. Other notes, for example those which refer to more than one correspondent, and background material, such as brochures and photocopied fragments of books of a more general nature, have been moved to Series X, Rita Gombrowicz Papers, Research Files. Many of the correspondence folders include translations of letters, some of which were made during Gombrowicz's lifetime and for his use (chiefly translations from English and German). Others are the result of Rita Gombrowicz's research (chiefly translations from Polish and Spanish).
Gombrowicz's personal correspondents include several members of his family. Of particular note is the correspondence of his brother Janusz Gombrowicz, which dates from 1948-67 and is continued, after Janusz's death, by his stepdaughter Stanislawa Cichowska. Other relatives among Gombrowicz's correspondents include Janusz Gombrowicz's wife Franciszka Gombrowicz, his sister Irena Gombrowicz, his brother Jerzy Gombrowicz, his nephew Józef Gombrowicz, his niece Teresa Gombrowicz, and his cousins Gustaw Kotkowski and Teresa Soltan. Correspondence between the writer and his siblings, Irena Gombrowicz and Jerzy Gombrowicz, can also be found on microfilm in Series IX, Personal Papers.
Many of Gombrowicz's friendships were of a personal and literary character. Perhaps the best example of this was his friendship with Constantin Jelenski. Their collaboration is documented by correspondence spanning the years 1956-69. These files then continue with correspondence between Jelenski and Rita Gombrowicz. This correspondence, most of which has been published, shows the important role Jelenski played in promoting Gombrowicz's literary career.
Other significant correspondents from Polish literary and cultural circles are the writers Tadeusz Breza, Zofia Chadzynska, Alexandra Orme (Litka de Barcza), Józef Czapski, Maria Dabrowska, Jaroslaw Iwaszkiewicz, Maria Szczepanska Kuncewiczowa, Czeslaw Milosz, Stanislaw Mrozek, Leopold Tyrmand, Kaimierz Wierzynski, Józef Wittlin, and Pawel Zdziechowski. Also represented are the painters Alicja Giangrande and Zygmunt Grocholski, the literary critic Artur Sandauer, the composer Zygmunt Mycielski, theater director Tadeusz Kantor, and the editor Jerzy Giedroyc.
Several of Gombrowicz's Polish emigré friends also are represented, including Maria Swieczewska and Karol Swieczewski. The Swieczewskis' correspondence (mostly photocopies) addresses a wide variety of topics, ranging from financial affairs to literary and personal concerns. Other Polish emigrés included in the series are Halina and Krzysztof Grodzicki, Rena Dzianott, and Ada Lubomirska. An extensive file of correspondence with Maria Paczowska and Bohdan Paczowski includes an interesting letter dictated by Gombrowicz to Rita and written in phonetic Polish. The bulk of this correspondence is written in Polish, with occasional letters in French.
Extensive files also exist for Witold Gombrowicz's Argentinian friends, Mariano Betelú, Juan Carlos Gomez, Jorge di Paola, and Miguel Grinberg. Files for Alejandro Rússovich, Sergio Rússovich, Beduino, Juan Carlos Ferreyra, and Enrique Wendt contain somewhat less correspondence. Witold Gombrowicz's wider contacts with Latin American literary and cultural circles are documented by correspondence with Virgilio Piñera, Roger Plá, Ernesto Sabato, Humberto Rodriguez Tomeu, Sergio Pitol, and Manuel Puig. All of the Latin American correspondence is in Spanish.
In addition to Gombrowicz's Polish and Latin American correspondents, the archive contains correspondence with many other outstanding personalities of the literary and art world of the mid-20th century. This group of letters, written chiefly in French, includes correspondence with Ingmar Bergman, François Bondy, Martin Buber, Albert Camus, Jean Dubuffet, Jean-Claude Hémery, Ernst Kreuder, Jorge Lavelli, and Alf Sjöberg. The series also contains a draft of a letter written by Gombrowicz to the French president Charles de Gaulles, and the replies on behalf of the president.
Gombrowicz's correspondence with editors, and his relationships with publishing houses, is also well represented. As a result, these files provide a rich source for the study of Gombrowicz's literary career and publication history. Extensive correspondence files exist between Gombrowicz and Jerzy Giedroyc, the Polish editor of Gombrowicz's works and publisher of the Paris-based Polish monthly Kultura. Most of the letters in these files are originals; problems with precise dating of the letters (no year date on the items) resulted in their being grouped by decade (1950s, 1960s), based on the letterhead or other annotations.
The bulk of the correspondence regarding French editions, including matters related to translations, can be found in the following files: Gallimard, Belfond, Denoël, Julliard, Lettres Nouvelles, Koukou Chanska, Geneviève Serreau, Maurice Nadeau, and Dominique de Roux. The rather complex history surrounding the publication of Witold Gombrowicz's works in French is explained in notes by Rita Gombrowicz (Series X, Rita Gombrowicz Papers, Research Files) and in her book Gombrowicz in Europe.
For Gombrowicz's German publishers, extensive documentation exists for Neske, S. Fischer Verlag, and R. Piper & Co. There are also files for Rowohlt, C. Bertelsmann Verlag, and Insel Verlag. Correspondence with Gombrowicz's German translator Walter Tiel is filed under Rudolf Richter (Tiel's real name).
English language editors are represented by several American publishers, including Grove Press, Harcourt Brace, Atlantic Monthly Press, Alfred Knopf, Viking Press, Harper and Row, Fawcett Publications Inc., Simon and Schuster, and Funk & Wagnalls Company. British publishers represented include Calder and Boyars Ltd. and Macgibbon & Kee.
Considerable files also exist for publishers in Argentina, Spain, Italy, Portugal, the Netherlands, Mexico, and Scandinavia, and for a few institutions, Radio Free Europe, the Ford Foundation, and Deutscher Akademischer Austauschdienst.
Gombrowicz's published correspondence (magazine publications and limited book editions) forms a subseries of Series V, Writings by Others About Gombrowicz. Photocopies of letters to Gombrowicz are included in the subseries Cahier de L'Herne: Gombrowicz.
Series II, Writings, is organized into five subseries: Novels, Plays, Shorter Works, Biographical Writings, and Other Writings. There are notes, holograph and typescript drafts, printed versions, translations by others of works by Gombrowicz, and publicity material. It should be noted that some of Gombrowicz's posthumously published writings (notes and drafts for the special issue of Cahier ) are to be found in Series V, Writings by Others About Gombrowicz.
The first subseries, Novels, is arranged alphabetically by title. The subseries includes the manuscript of Gombrowicz's last novel, Kosmos, in several redactions, and a complete French translation of Trans-Atlantyk by Koukou Chanska and François Marié. Material pertaining to Gombrowicz's three other novels ( Ferdydurke, Opetani, and Pornografia ) is considerably less extensive, consisting of drafts of prefaces and publicity material for various editions.
Plays, also arranged by title, includes drafts of Historia (the first version of Operetka, published posthumously in 1975) and four versions of Operetka, written between 1958-66. In these drafts, and others, one can observe Gombrowicz's writing method, as described in Dziennik 1953-56 (Instytut Literacki, 1957), characterized by his picking up thoughts and phrases and rewriting rather than correcting earlier drafts.
Shorter Works includes drafts and printed versions of Gombrowicz's short stories, articles, interviews, open letters to editors, and other submissions. Also included are translations by others of some of his shorter works. Much of the material consists of originals, but it is also supplemented by photocopies. The subseries includes works by Gombrowicz written under the pen names Jorge Alejandro, Andrzej Frycz, and Komentator. The subseries is arranged alphabetically by title.
Autobiographical Writings contains manuscripts, some complete and some incomplete, of all of Gombrowicz's major autobiographical pieces. The subseries includes: two typescript fragments of Dziennik 1953-56; various holograph redactions of fragments of Dziennik 1962-67; various redactions, in holograph and typescript, of fragments of Dziennik 1967-69; a holograph manuscript of Entretiens avec Gombrowicz; and a typescript manuscript of Wspomnienia polskie/Wedrówki po Argentynie.
The subseries Other Writings is divided into Notes on Philosophy (including Gombrowicz's notes and drafts), Guide de la philosophie en six heures un quart (containing notes taken by Rita Gombrowicz during the philosophy course conducted by the writer and published posthumously), and Miscellaneous, which contains Gombrowicz's more ephemeral writings, often not intended for publication, as well as publicity material.
Series III, Adaptations by Others of Works by Gombrowicz, contains theater scenarios, film treatments, and additional material related to adaptations of works by Gombrowicz. The series is organized by title of adapted work and further subdivided by the language of the adaptation.
Series IV, Theater Programs, is organized by the title of a play or adapted work and further arranged by the language of the text. There is an additional section for festivals. Some of the folders include leaflets and newspaper clippings found with the programs. Oversize clippings have been moved to Series XI, Clippings. Photographs found with the programs have been moved to Series VIII, Photographs.
Series V, Writings of Others About Gombrowicz is organized into seven subseries: Cahier de L'Herne: Gombrowicz, Published Letters, Bibliography, Articles, Biographical Articles and Notes, Transcripts of Radio Broadcasts, Theses and Student Essays. The series consists of works written by others during Gombrowicz's lifetime and after his death. Files on other works to which third parties made significant contributions, as co-author ( Entretiens avec Dominique de Roux ) or editor ( Historia and Guide de la philosophie en six heures un quart ), are to be found in Series II, Writings.
Writings of Others About Gombrowicz includes the special issue of Cahier de L'Herne: Gombrowicz. Gombrowicz was involved in the preparation of this issue, but it was edited by Constantin Jelenski and Dominique de Roux and published only after Gombrowicz's death. The subseries includes outlines of the contents of the issue, Gombrowicz's notes and drafts, articles sent by various contributors, and working files containing photocopies of correspondence, often duplicating letters in Series I, Correspondence.
Published Letters contains publications of Gombrowicz's correspondence with Adam Mauersberg, Irena and Bogdan Osadczuk, Artur Sandauer, Bruno Schulz, and Józef Wittlin. Letters were published in literary magazines, newspapers, and limited editions.
Bibliography is organized into general bibliography, bibliography by country of publication, and bibliography of translations. It includes original material as well as photocopies of fragments of books and library catalogs.
Articles contains both original and photocopied material. Photocopies predominate, but the subseries also includes manuscripts and typescripts of articles by Constantin Jelenski, a printed version of an article by Peter Kliemann annotated by Gombrowicz, and computer printouts of articles by Alejandro Rússovich.
Biographical Articles and Notes contains chiefly photocopies of printed material.
Transcripts of Radio Broadcasts contains mainly broadcasts of German language radio stations. Also included are broadcasts of Radio Free Europe. The subseries is arranged alphabetically by company name.
Theses and Student Papers is comprised chiefly of masters (maîtrise) theses. Additional student essays, chiefly in French, are included.
Series VI, Commemorative Works and Activities, documents the efforts undertaken to commemorate Witold Gombrowicz, both at the time of his death and in later years. The bulk of the material dates from 1969-70, the period shortly following the writer's death, and from 1989 into the early 1990s, at the time of the 20th anniversary of his death. The series is organized into five subseries: Obituaries and Tributes; Association des Amis de Witold Gombrowicz; Vingt Ans Après; "Witold Gombrowicz", Centre George Pompidou, Paris; and Other Events.
Obituaries and Tributes contains newspaper clippings, transcripts of radio broadcasts, and press releases issued during the first months after Gombrowicz's death. Letters of condolence and records of a more private character are to be found in Series X, Rita Gombrowicz Papers. The material in the rest of the series is diverse and often interrelated. It includes correspondence, organizational records of the Association des Amis de Witold Gombrowicz, articles sent in reply to a call for submissions for the commemorative publication Vingt ans après, and documentation related to "Witold Gombrowicz," an exhibition organized at the Centre Georges Pompidou in Paris in 1991, as well as other events, including the presentation of the Pompidou exhibition in Vence and Berlin.
Series VII, Audiovisual materials, includes both Audio Recordings and Moving Image Media. Audio Recordings encompasses the recordings of programs about Gombrowicz and the adaptations of his works for radio. The subseries is arranged alphabetically by the name of agency or person chiefly responsible for the recording. The tapes have been reformatted on digital discs (CDs) for reference use. The originals are stored in Restricted Fragile. The Moving Image Media include amateur films by Mariano Betelú, documentaries about Gombrowicz, and the theater and film productions of his works. The original films have been reformatted to DVD discs for reference use. Originals are stored in Restricted Fragile.